<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science | Data Science Masterpiece</title>
    <link>/categories/data-science/</link>
      <atom:link href="/categories/data-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Data Science</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Data Science</title>
      <link>/categories/data-science/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick deep dive at Data Scientist Skill set</title>
      <link>/2020/01/17/quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2020/01/17/quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;One year ago, when I truly and seriously considered improving my skill in Data Science, two questions were always lingering in my mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What truly are the skills that a Data Scientist needs?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What skill will support me in the future and How do I improve myself in the right direction at the most efficacy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And many other friends, acquaintances reached out to me for a thought of what to learn to become a Data Scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, I can share some of my experiences with them, but as you’ve already known, this field evolves unpreceedingly fast, technology and new required skills change on the yearly basis at the slowest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What you learn today will be the old of tomorrow!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, when I was known of the Kaggle dataset on Survey of Data Science and Machine learning, this data will definitely give me some insights for my questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Data source is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/c/kaggle-survey-2019&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will summary my key findings from the survey. The complete analysis can be found through this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/geninhu/direction-toward-a-great-data-scientist/data&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This analysis uses R language with tidyverse package for the best insight visualization.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;role-and-responsibilities&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Role and Responsibilities:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Data scientist’ is ’s responsibility for many tasks with top 3 are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analyzing data&lt;/strong&gt; to influence product or to support business decisions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explore new areas of Machine learning&lt;/strong&gt; through builidng prototypes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experiment to &lt;strong&gt;improve company existing Machine learning models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/geniusnhu/ds-masterpiece-hugo/master/content/post/2020-01-17-quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/responsibility.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;programming-skills&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programming skills:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python, SQL and R&lt;/strong&gt; are all the programming languages that are essential for Data Scientist as they stand in the Top 3 respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/geniusnhu/ds-masterpiece-hugo/master/content/post/2020-01-17-quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/PL.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;450&#34; &gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;machine-learning-skills&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Machine Learning skills:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not a surprise if all Data Scientists use Machine Learning in their daily job but I was amazed that almost all of them use both Natural Language Processing and Computer Vision. These 2 fields has no longer been specified areas to some groups of users but expanded to much wider application and require Data Scientist to own these skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;machine-learning-algorithm-skills&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Machine Learning algorithm skills:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regression&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Tree-based algorithms&lt;/strong&gt; are the models used by Data Scientist. With the long history in statistics and analytics, these models are still being favor in analyzing data. Another advantage of these traditional models is that they are easy to explain to business partner. Other models such as Neuron network, or Deep learning is hard to explain the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/geniusnhu/ds-masterpiece-hugo/master/content/post/2020-01-17-quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/ML.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting thing is that 51% of Data scientists is applying &lt;strong&gt;Boosting method&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;python-skills&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python skills:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scikit-learn, Keras, Xgboost, TensorFlow and RandomForest libraries&lt;/strong&gt; are the top used frameworks given their benefit and convenience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/geniusnhu/ds-masterpiece-hugo/master/content/post/2020-01-17-quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/package.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;450&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;data-scientist-credential&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Scientist Credential:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foundation skills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Writing code is an important skill of a good Data scientist. You do not need to be an excellent coder to be a Data scientist but it is dangerous to think that knowing little of coding skill is just enough to work as a Data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is essential to build up your business skills in addition to technical skills. Many data scientists, especially the junior excels at machine learning and coding but is lack of a business point of view so that most of their work does not support the business as the way it should be. Their recommendations were far from what the company is doing and it ended up beating all of their effort. That is the worst thing you want to face in the world of Data science when no one thinks your idea valuable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specialized skills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Familiar with and expert in Python, SQL and/or R on various online/offline platforms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fluency in using Local development environments and Intergrated development Environment, including but not limited to Jupyter, RStudio, Pycharm. Try to &lt;strong&gt;learn on job&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;learn on practice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strong foundation with practical experience in Linear/Logistics regression, Decision Tree/Random Forest, and Gradient Boosting models. Moreover, besides popular and must known libraries such as Scikit-learn, Keras, Tensorflow, Xgboost is the framework that student should learn at the moment. Working on your own project/cooperating project is a good choice to get practical experience if you have not obtained the chance in a company.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Computer Vision and NLP are the booming areas in Data science so it is beneficial to prepare yourself with these skills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although AutoML is a newly emerging field, it will probably become one of the important tools and skills for Data Scientist, including Automated hyperparameter tuning, Data augmentation, Feature engineering/selection and Auto ML pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Skills in working with Big data and Big data products e.g Google Bigquerry, Databricks, Redshift are the must to own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the same with usage of cloud computing skills. In big company, it is a common to work on cloud so if you do not know how to conduct machine learning on cloud, it will become your minus comparing to other candidates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And one last important thing: &lt;strong&gt;Always believe in yourself, your choice and never give up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
