<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science with Nhu Hoang</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Data Science with Nhu Hoang</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Nhu Hoang</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Data Science with Nhu Hoang</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>/talk/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt; button above to view the built-in slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides can be added in a few ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create&lt;/strong&gt; slides using Academic&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; feature and link using &lt;code&gt;slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upload&lt;/strong&gt; an existing slide deck to &lt;code&gt;static/&lt;/code&gt; and link using &lt;code&gt;url_slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embed&lt;/strong&gt; your slides (e.g. Google Slides) or presentation video on this page using &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further talk details can easily be added to this page using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practical flow of a Data Science Project</title>
      <link>/2020/01/26/practical-flow-of-a-data-science-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2020/01/26/practical-flow-of-a-data-science-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After 5 years of working in field of Analytics and Data Science in 2 multinational companies, the things that I learned through several failures and achievements are that the real bottleneck of a Data Scientist is the understanding of the data scientist&#39;s consumer rather than the technical side of running the right method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will try to make this post condense in key points because practical application can vary in various forms and patterns, and it highly depends on the situation of a Data scientist&#39;s work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-clarify-business-question&#34;&gt;1. Clarify Business question&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my years in analytics and data science, in addition to technological concept explanation, &lt;strong&gt;business question clarification&lt;/strong&gt; is one of the most difficult tasks when a Data scientist communicates with business partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason is that the business partner always asks very general question such as &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I want to know why sales declined?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;How to increase the efficiency of the promotion activity for brand A during summer?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you hear these questions, can you imagine the right approach or the answer to the case? I am sure that you will be very vague and confused, and if you deliver the result based on this current understanding, it is a high possibility that the business partners will say &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;This is not what I need&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OMG! How terrible it is when you spent so much effort into this, but no one values it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is because you did not touch the right pain point!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that the common advice is to ask &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; in order to dig into the real problems. However, this solution is not applicable all times because the business partners might not know why for all of your questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that helped me overcome this difficulty is to &lt;strong&gt;imagine the outcome that I desire&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-identify-the-approach-for-the-problem&#34;&gt;2. Identify the approach for the problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part is to set the methodology for the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever faced a situation where you do not know which approach to be used between descriptive analysis, predictive analysis, classification, segmentation, time series forecasting, etc.?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linear Regression cannot be used to segment customers or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Descriptive analysis cannot predict customer churn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This step seems to be easy but in fact quickly got confused. If the Sales Director asked Data Science team to forecast the &lt;strong&gt;sales for next year&lt;/strong&gt;, and the business need is to get the forecast &lt;strong&gt;based on the amount of budget spending&lt;/strong&gt;, then which model should be used?
If the business wanted the forecast &lt;strong&gt;based on the market movement&lt;/strong&gt;, which approach is suitable?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the importance in choosing the right approach for the business question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-acquire-the-appropriate-data&#34;&gt;3. Acquire the appropriate data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After identifying the business questions and the approach above, set up data requirement and extract the appropriate data from the data warehouse are the next thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data selection sounds to be straightforward but indeed complicated. To solve the business questions, which kind of data is in need of. For example, will it need to have the birthday information of the customer if the task is to predict their churn probability?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, identify the approach to acquire the data. This can be from company&#39;s data warehouse, conducting survey collecting result, or government-owned data&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What occurs during Data Collection?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the foreseen problems is the &lt;strong&gt;unavailability of data&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This problem is very common in real case in which data is unable to capture at the moment of collection such as &lt;em&gt;the time spent in using a non-digital product&lt;/em&gt;. As a common sense, you will think that you have to get the data. However, you have to consider the consequences of getting data including cost, time, resources and if the data is indeed not too important to your model, all the effort you put into it will be down the drain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the solution for this case is to defer inaccessible data and in case the model requires this data for a better result, you will have more confident to invest in obtaining it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the provident ways of getting new features is to change the system of collecting data to acquire the right information needed. The Data scientist team can discuss with data management to get the timestamp that customers log on the page in addition to the browsing/ purchasing data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the Data scientist is unable to acquire unavailable data through the above way, then think about contacting an outside data owner and prepare the budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After getting all the data you need, the next step is thing that a Data scientist usually does:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EDA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data cleaning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Validation choosing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model selection/Building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model tuning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensemble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The order can be flexible and this is the standard progress that I usually do in my project and my job. Sometimes, after tuning and the accuracy does not meet my expectation, I need to go back to the feature engineering step to find other way to deal with features.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick deep dive at Data Scientist Skill set</title>
      <link>/2020/01/17/quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2020/01/17/quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;One year ago, when I truly and seriously considered improving my skill in Data Science, two questions were always lingering in my mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What truly are the skills that a Data Scientist needs?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What skill will support me in the future and How do I improve myself in the right direction at the most efficacy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And many other friends, acquaintances reached out to me for a thought of what to learn to become a Data Scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, I can share some of my experiences with them, but as you’ve already known, this field evolves unpreceedingly fast, technology and new required skills change on the yearly basis at the slowest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What you learn today will be the old of tomorrow!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, when I was known of the Kaggle dataset on Survey of Data Science and Machine learning, this data will definitely give me some insights for my questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Data source is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/c/kaggle-survey-2019&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will summary my key findings from the survey. The complete analysis can be found through this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/geninhu/direction-toward-a-great-data-scientist/data&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This analysis uses R language with tidyverse package for the best insight visualization.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;role-and-responsibilities&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Role and Responsibilities:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Data scientist’ is ’s responsibility for many tasks with top 3 are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analyzing data&lt;/strong&gt; to influence product or to support business decisions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explore new areas of Machine learning&lt;/strong&gt; through builidng prototypes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experiment to &lt;strong&gt;improve company existing Machine learning models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/geniusnhu/ds-masterpiece-hugo/master/content/post/2020-01-17-quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/responsibility.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;programming-skills&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programming skills:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python, SQL and R&lt;/strong&gt; are all the programming languages that are essential for Data Scientist as they stand in the Top 3 respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/geniusnhu/ds-masterpiece-hugo/master/content/post/2020-01-17-quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/PL.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;450&#34; &gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;machine-learning-skills&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Machine Learning skills:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not a surprise if all Data Scientists use Machine Learning in their daily job but I was amazed that almost all of them use both Natural Language Processing and Computer Vision. These 2 fields has no longer been specified areas to some groups of users but expanded to much wider application and require Data Scientist to own these skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;machine-learning-algorithm-skills&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Machine Learning algorithm skills:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regression&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Tree-based algorithms&lt;/strong&gt; are the models used by Data Scientist. With the long history in statistics and analytics, these models are still being favor in analyzing data. Another advantage of these traditional models is that they are easy to explain to business partner. Other models such as Neuron network, or Deep learning is hard to explain the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/geniusnhu/ds-masterpiece-hugo/master/content/post/2020-01-17-quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/ML.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting thing is that 51% of Data scientists is applying &lt;strong&gt;Boosting method&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;python-skills&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python skills:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scikit-learn, Keras, Xgboost, TensorFlow and RandomForest libraries&lt;/strong&gt; are the top used frameworks given their benefit and convenience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/geniusnhu/ds-masterpiece-hugo/master/content/post/2020-01-17-quick-deep-dive-at-data-scientist-skill-set/package.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;450&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;data-scientist-credential&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Scientist Credential:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foundation skills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Writing code is an important skill of a good Data scientist. You do not need to be an excellent coder to be a Data scientist but it is dangerous to think that knowing little of coding skill is just enough to work as a Data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is essential to build up your business skills in addition to technical skills. Many data scientists, especially the junior excels at machine learning and coding but is lack of a business point of view so that most of their work does not support the business as the way it should be. Their recommendations were far from what the company is doing and it ended up beating all of their effort. That is the worst thing you want to face in the world of Data science when no one thinks your idea valuable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specialized skills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Familiar with and expert in Python, SQL and/or R on various online/offline platforms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fluency in using Local development environments and Intergrated development Environment, including but not limited to Jupyter, RStudio, Pycharm. Try to &lt;strong&gt;learn on job&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;learn on practice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strong foundation with practical experience in Linear/Logistics regression, Decision Tree/Random Forest, and Gradient Boosting models. Moreover, besides popular and must known libraries such as Scikit-learn, Keras, Tensorflow, Xgboost is the framework that student should learn at the moment. Working on your own project/cooperating project is a good choice to get practical experience if you have not obtained the chance in a company.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Computer Vision and NLP are the booming areas in Data science so it is beneficial to prepare yourself with these skills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although AutoML is a newly emerging field, it will probably become one of the important tools and skills for Data Scientist, including Automated hyperparameter tuning, Data augmentation, Feature engineering/selection and Auto ML pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Skills in working with Big data and Big data products e.g Google Bigquerry, Databricks, Redshift are the must to own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the same with usage of cloud computing skills. In big company, it is a common to work on cloud so if you do not know how to conduct machine learning on cloud, it will become your minus comparing to other candidates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And one last important thing: &lt;strong&gt;Always believe in yourself, your choice and never give up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides</title>
      <link>/slides/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/slides/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;create-slides-in-markdown-with-academic&#34;&gt;Create slides in Markdown with Academic&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/&#34;&gt;Academic&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiently write slides in Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-in-1: Create, Present, and Publish your slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports speaker notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile friendly slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;controls&#34;&gt;Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next: &lt;code&gt;Right Arrow&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previous: &lt;code&gt;Left Arrow&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start: &lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish: &lt;code&gt;End&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overview: &lt;code&gt;Esc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaker notes: &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fullscreen: &lt;code&gt;F&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoom: &lt;code&gt;Alt + Click&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hakimel/reveal.js#pdf-export&#34;&gt;PDF Export&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-highlighting&#34;&gt;Code Highlighting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inline code: &lt;code&gt;variable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code block:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;porridge = &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;
if porridge == &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;:
    print(&amp;quot;Eating...&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;math&#34;&gt;Math&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In-line math: $x + y = z$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Block math:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
f\left( x \right) = ;\frac{{2\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x - 4} \right)}}{{\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x + 1} \right)}}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fragments&#34;&gt;Fragments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make content appear incrementally&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{% fragment %}} One {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} **Two** {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} Three {{% /fragment %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt; to play!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
One
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Two&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
Three
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fragment can accept two optional parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;class&lt;/code&gt;: use a custom style (requires definition in custom CSS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;weight&lt;/code&gt;: sets the order in which a fragment appears&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;speaker-notes&#34;&gt;Speaker Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add speaker notes to your presentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{% speaker_note %}}
- Only the speaker can read these notes
- Press `S` key to view
{{% /speaker_note %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press the &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view the speaker notes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only the speaker can read these notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;themes&#34;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;black: Black background, white text, blue links (default)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;white: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;league: Gray background, white text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beige: Beige background, dark text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sky: Blue background, thin dark text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;night: Black background, thick white text, orange links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serif: Cappuccino background, gray text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simple: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;solarized: Cream-colored background, dark green text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;section data-noprocess data-shortcode-slide
  
      
      data-background-image=&#34;/img/boards.jpg&#34;
  &gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-slide&#34;&gt;Custom Slide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customize the slide style and background&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{&amp;lt; slide background-image=&amp;quot;/img/boards.jpg&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide background-color=&amp;quot;#0000FF&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide class=&amp;quot;my-style&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-css-example&#34;&gt;Custom CSS Example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s make headers navy colored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;assets/css/reveal_custom.css&lt;/code&gt; with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-css&#34;&gt;.reveal section h1,
.reveal section h2,
.reveal section h3 {
  color: navy;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://spectrum.chat/academic&#34;&gt;Ask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terms</title>
      <link>/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/terms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
